Phyllis Kihn research collection
Connecticut Historical Society
Phyllis Kihn research collection
1870-1998
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Kihn, Phyllis
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
Historical Sketch
The Educational Mission in Hartford, Connecticut, was the fulfillment of a dream of Yung Wing. He wanted Chinese youth to study American technology to improve China’s engineering and infrastructure. Yung Wing came to the United States in 1847 to study at Monson Academy in Massachusetts and at Yale. It was upon his return to China that he began planning to send Chinese students to America.
A group of thirty students ranging in age from ten to fourteen arrived in Hartford in 1872. They lived with host families, attended local schools, and in the summer studied Chinese classics at the Mission’s headquarters at 352 Collins Street, Hartford. In 1881 the Chinese government recalled the students because they were becoming too Americanized.
Scope and Content
The collection was given the accession number of the first gift to the Historical Society, a scrapbook donated by Phyllis Kihn. The other materials were donated at a later time by Kihn and were also gathered when the Historical Society developed an exhibit about the Mission for the Chinese Students Memorial Association in 2001.
Box 1 contains photocopies of lists of Chinese students in New England, catalogs from Wesleyan Academy in Massachusetts, research notes, articles by and about the students, and biographical information about them. Box 2 also contains a large number of photocopies of research materials including articles about the founder, Yung Wing, and about the mission in general, Chinese periodicals, letters in Chinese that have not been translated, correspondence about the Historical Society’s research of the mission, and collection finding aids from other repositories. The third box contains a scrapbook of newspaper clippings compiled by Phyllis Kihn.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Yung, Wing, 1828-1912.
Subjects
Chinese -- United States.; Chinese Educational Commission.; Scrapbooks.
Contents:
- Chinese Educational Mission
  - Lists of Chinese students in Connecticut and New England schools, 1872-1880 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Catalogs, program, lists from Wesleyan Academy (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles, Chinese students, Springfield, Mass., 1871-1880 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photocopies of photographs of the cornerstone laying at South Church, Springfield, Mass. and of a football team, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Research notes, articles copied from Hartford newspapers by Phyllis Kahn, 1872-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Transcriptions of articles from Hartford newspapers, 1875-1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Copies of articles about the Chinese Educational Mission, 1875-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Census record notes, homes of host families, 1880-1888 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photocopies of photographs of the Hartford homes of Chinese students (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Copies of articles. A.G. Robinson, The Senior Returned Students, 1932 and E.C. Gardner, An Autobiography, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Copy of a book by Thomas E. La Fargue, China’s First Hundred, 1942 and a list of corrections (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Articles. Helen G. Williams, International Living—An Old Experiment, 1966 and an anonymous article, Jeme Tien Yow: The Man Who Laid the Tracks from Peiping to Kalgan, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Biographical Directory, Chinese students, compiled by Phyllis Kihn (2 volumes), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Biographical notes on Chinese students, compiled by Phyllis Kihn, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Biographical notes on Chinese students, compiled by Phyllis Kihn, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photocopies of photographs of the Chinese students, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Typescripts of Hartford Courant articles, 1891-1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Articles about Yung Wing, 1965; Princeton-in-Asia, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scope and content note for Yung Wing papers at Yale University, 1981 (Box 2, Folder B.)
  - Genealogy of Jane Kellogg Yung Wing, 1914 (Box 2, Folder C.)
  - Copies of autographs, Chinese and English (Box 2, Folder D.)
  - Articles about and lists of Chinese students returning to China (Box 2, Folder E.)
  - Copies of research materials compiled by Phyllis Kihn, 1878-1906, 1972 (Box 2, Folder F.)
  - Research materials compiled by Phyllis Kihn, 1906-1970 (Box 2, Folder G.)
  - Articles from the CHS Bulletin (Box 2, Folder H.)
  - Chinese periodical, four issues, 1972 (Box 2, Folder I-IA.)
  - Copies of articles written in Chinese. Timothy Kao, about Jeme Tien Yow, 1972-1974; Arthur G. Robinson, Pilgrims to the Western Seats of Learning, 1932; E.C. Gardner, An Autobiography, n.d. (Box 2, Folder J.)
  - Copies of letters written in Chinese. Not translated. (Box 2, Folder K.)
  - Copy of a booklet by J. DeFrancis, Beginning Chinese, 1963 (Box 2, Folder L.)
  - Notes on Chinese language (Box 2, Folder M.)
  - Correspondence of Connecticut Historical Society while researching the mission, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder N.)
  - Correspondence and notes regarding the Empire Reform Association, 1971 (Box 2, Folder O.)
  - Photocopy of photograph of SS City of Peking (Box 2, Folder P.)
  - History of Young Chinese Students in America, 1872-1881: Letters of the Chinese Educational Commission Students, edited by Timothy Kao (Box 2, Folder Q)
  - Jeme Tien Yow and the Chinese Railway, by Timothy Kao and H. Ling (Box 2, Folder R.)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous materials regarding the Chinese Students Memorial Society reception at the Historical Society, 36060 (Box 2, Folder S.)
  - Exhibition labels (Box 2, Folder T.)
  - Finding aid to Thomas La Fargue papers at Washington State University, 1987 (Box 2, Folder U.)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper articles about the Mission, collected and compiled by Phyllis Kihn. (Box 3, Folder A.)